Guide to the Edgar Parin and Ingri D'Aulaire Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edgar Parin and Ingri D'Aulaire Papers
1909-1985
GEN MSS 874
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
62.56
(187 boxes) + 8 broadsides, 39 rolls and 1 record album storage
The collection consists of art work, writings, notes and research papers, correspondence, printed material, motion picture film, art supplies, photographs and other related papers, documenting the D'Aulaires' creative process and collaborative work as authors and illustrators of children's books.
D'Aulaire, Edgar Parin, 1898-1986
D'Aulaire, Ingri, 1904-1980
General note
This finding aid describes a collection that has been acquired by the library in discrete segments over time. The narrative sections of the finding aid provide information about the content and context of the collection. The >Collection Contents section provides a general description and in some instances a box or folder listing of the various acquisitions of the collection. The Processing Notes section provides information about the way and extent to which the library has processed this collection. The Arrangement section provides information about how material within this collection is organized and tips on how to locate material across various acquisitions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Nils Daulaire and Per Ola D'Aulaire on the Jockey Hollow Fund, 2006.
Gift of Nils Daulaire and Per Ola D'Aulaire, 2006-2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Record Album Storage, Box 3 (commercial record album): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 172-189 (motion picture films and reel-to-reel sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 190 (videocassette and DVD): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 230-233 (lithograph stones): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Edgar Parin D'Aulaire (1898-1986) and Ingri D'Aulaire (1904-1980)
Edgar Parin D'Aulaire and Ingri Mortenson D'Aulaire authored and illustrated a number of children's books. Throughout their joint career, which spanned nearly five decades, the D'Aulaires worked as a team on the text and illustrations for numerous children's books. Their published works include: Abraham Lincoln (1939), Foxie (1949), Buffalo Bill (1952), Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths (1962), Norse Gods and Giants (1967), and D'Aulaires' Trolls (1972), among many others.
Ingri Mortenson was born on December 27, 1904 in Kongsberg, Norway to Per and Oline Mortenson. She studied art at the Institute of Arts and Crafts in Oslo, Norway, Hans Hofman School of Art in Munich, Germany, and Academie Scandinave, Academie Gauguin, and Academie Andre L'Hote in Paris, France.
Edgar Parin was born on September 30, 1898 in Munich, Germany, to Gino and Ella Parin. Edgar Parin adopted his mother's maiden name, D'Aulaire, for his professional identity. D'Aulaire attended the Technological Institute of Munich and Hans Hofman School of Art in Munich, Germany before continuing his studies in Paris (including a period as a pupil of Henri Matisse).
Ingri Mortenson and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire met while attending the Hans Hofman School of Art and were married on July 24, 1925. After living and studying in Paris the D'Aulaires immigrated to the United States in 1929 settling in New York and then Connecticut. In 1930 they began collaborating on children's books with their first publication The Magic Rug appearing in 1931. The D'Aulaires drew inspiration from Norwegian folktales and American historical figures for their work. In 1940 the D'Aulaires were awarded a Caldecott Medal from the American Library Association for Abraham Lincoln. Other recognition includes the Catholic Library Association Regina Medal (1970) and a nomination for the National Book Award (1973).
The D'Aulaires had two sons: Per Ola and Nils Maarten.
Ingri D'Aulaire died of cancer on October 24, 1980. Edgar D'Aulaire died on May 1, 1986.
Scope and Contents
The Edgar Parin and Ingri D'Aulaire Papers document the D'Aulaires' creative process and collaborative work as authors and illustrators of children's books. The papers are comprised of artwork (including drawings and sketches), writings (manuscripts and research papers), correspondence, printed material, motion picture film, art supplies, photographs, and other related papers. The papers provide evidence of the D'Aulaires' creative life and shed light into the production of popular American children's literature during the twentieth-century.
A broad range of the D'Aulaires' professional life is reflected in the papers from their early collaboration on The Magic Rug (1931) to publications produced during the 1970s, such as D'Aulaires' Trolls (1972). In addition the papers are comprised of documents relating to various points in their creative process. Autograph manuscripts and typescripts provide insight into earlier phases of the production process whereas proofs and galleys reveal the involvement of printers and publishers. Copper plates and lithograph stones provide further insight into the production of the D'Aulaires' books. Their artistic life is also reflected in various objects such as art supplies and a documentary film Children of the Northlights.
The papers also include correspondence, photographs, home movies, and personal effects, which are a window into the D'Aulaires' personal lives.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: I. February 2006 Acquisition, 1931-1976. II. March 2006 Acquisition, 1930-1978. III. March 2006 Acquisition, 1930. IV. September 2007 Acquisition, 1909-1985.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, art work and drawings can be found in most, if not all, of the groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Children's literature, American -- 20th Century; Illustration of books -- United States; Illustrators, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Picture books for children -- United States; Illustrations (layout features); Motion pictures (visual works); Slides (photographs); D'Aulaire, Edgar Parin, 1898-1986; D'Aulaire, Ingri, 1904-1980
- I. February 2006 Acquisition, 1931-1976; 38.13 linear ft. (96 boxes) + 7 broadsides, 37 rolls
  Arrangement
  Organized into seven groupings: Material Housed in Manuscript Boxes, Material Housed in Custom Manuscript Boxes, Oversize Material, Objects, Audiovisual Material, Rolled Items, and Broadside Folders. Arranged alphabetically by title of work within groupings.
  Scope and Contents
  This portion of the collection contains extensive material relating to the D'Aulaires' work as authors and illustrators. The span of the D'Aulaires' career is well documented from some of their earlier works, such as The Magic Rug (1931), to later works, such as D'Aulaires Trolls (1972). Their creative process can be traced in autograph manuscripts, typescripts, drawings, lithograph prints, acetate prints, proofs, galleys, paste-ups, and research notes. Also included are objects and other material relating to their publications, such as copper plates from East of the Sun and West of the Moon and a record album for Columbus.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 844.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Similar material can also be found in II. March 2006 Acquisition, III. March 2006 Acquisition, and IV. September 2007 Acquisition.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from Nils Daulaire and Per Ola D'Aulaire on the Jockey Hollow Fund, 2006.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Record Album Storage, Box 3 (commercial record album): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Material Housed in Manuscript Boxes
    - Abraham Lincoln
      - Double-sided autograph manuscript guide sheet, circa 1939 (Box 1)
      - "Young Wings," 2 issues, circa 1939 (Box 1)
      - "Brooklyn Public Library Bulletin", circa 1939 (Box 1)
      - "Abe Lincoln Quarterly", circa 1939 (Box 1)
      - "Horn Book Quarterly", circa 1939 (Box 1)
    - Animals Everywhere
      - Publishers catalogs, circa 1940; 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Exhibition catalog, circa 1940 (Box 1)
    - Children of the Northlights
      - Preliminary sketches with some notes and text, circa 1935 (Box 1)
      - Unbound publisher's proofs with end paper designs and unbound publisher's proof for library edition, circa 1935 (Box 1)
      - Publisher's catalogs, circa 1935; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - The Conquest of the Atlantic
      - 9 drawings, circa 1933 (Box 1)
      - Small proofs, circa 1933 (Box 1)
      - Dust jacket, circa 1935 (Box 1)
    - East of the Sun and West of the Moon
      - Story guide sheet; 4 typescript pages of indexes; 1 manuscript page text; 1 manuscript page indexes; 4 preliminary sketches, circa 1969 (Box 1)
      - Signature folders beginning with dedication probably for 1969 edition; paste up proofs with number of preliminary sketches and drawings some with handwritten text, each folder lined with text; some proof text mounted; end papers, circa 1969 (Box 1)
      - 3 preliminary sketches, circa 1969 (Box 1)
      - Author's galley with some handwritten corrections, circa 1969 (Box 1)
    - Foxie
      - Unbound proof and dust jacket with 4 unsewn signatures, circa 1949 (Box 1)
      - Publisher's proof, incomplete, circa 1949 (Box 1)
      - Acetates and film, circa 1949 (Box 1)
      - Acetates and film, circa 1949; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - George Washington
      - Small color and black and white proofs, circa 1936 (Box 2)
    - Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths
      - Unbound publisher's proofs, circa 1962 (Box 2)
      - Unbound proofs, circa 1962 (Box 2)
      - Unbound proof sets: 2 complete proofs; 1 variant unbound proof; 4 incomplete unbound proofs, circa 1962; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Unbound proof sets: 2 complete proofs; 1 variant unbound proof; 4 incomplete unbound proofs, circa 1962; 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Set of galleys, circa 1962 (Box 3)
    - Leif the Lucky
      - Papers relating to zinc impressions and cost sheets, circa 1941 (Box 3)
      - Rolled illustrations on linen, circa 1941; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - The Lord's Prayer
      - Original hand-colored design for title page; complete set of proofs, circa 1934 (Box 3)
      - Dust jackets for Catholic and Protestant editions in various states; proof for title page and end papers, circa 1934 (Box 3)
    - The Magic Meadow
      - Typescript, corrected, drawings, sketches, circa 1958 (Box 3)
      - Typed pages with notes; separate pages of notes and corrections, circa 1958 (Box 3)
      - Typed pages in Norwegian with handwritten notes, circa 1958 (Box 3)
      - Unbound paste-up in 4 galleys plus end papers, pictorial title in pen and ink, circa 1958 (Box 3)
      - Unbound proof with trial proof for dust jacket; unbound publisher's proof in 4 signatures, circa 1958 (Box 4)
      - Galley on newspaper print with drawings, chalk drawing and notes, circa 1958 (Box 4)
      - Original chalk drawings, circa 1958; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Unbound publisher's proof in 4 gatherings; 2 color proofs, photostat of title and fronts, circa 1958 (Box 4)
    - Nils
      - Sketchbook, circa 1948 (Box 4)
    - Norse Gods and Giants
      - Preliminary drawings and sketches, some paste-ups, corrected, circa 1967; 3 (Box 4)
      - Research, circa 1967 (Box 4)
      - Notes; pencil sketch of title page; color illustrations in mixed media; pen and ink sketches, circa 1967 (Box 4)
      - Unbound publisher's proof, circa 1967 (Box 4)
      - Unbound publisher's proof, circa 1967; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Ola and Blakken and Line, Sine, Trine
      - Swedish festival; 4 typed pages based on Ola, circa 1933 (Box 5)
      - Pencil drawing, circa 1967 (Box 5)
    - The Terrible Troll-Bird
      - Second dummy, 1973-75; with preliminary sketches laid in front; 37 pages with illustrations and pasted text, some illustrations highlighted with color; with color proof or dust jacket, with original drawing on acetate; also laid in are some notes and text layout., 1973-1975 (Box 5)
      - Color proofs, circa 1976 (Box 5)
      - Unbound publisher's proofs in three signatures in dust jacket, unbound publisher's proof, circa 1976 (Box 5)
      - Sketches, circa 1976 (Box 6)
      - Proofs in gatherings in various states, circa 1976; 5 (Box 6)
      - Autograph manuscript and typescript, some with corrections, circa 1976 (Box 6)
      - Unbound publisher's proofs, three gatherings, circa 1976 (Box 6)
    - Too Big
      - Matted color proofs and five black and white proofs of same image; black and white proof with colored drawing on verso, circa 1945; 9 (Box 6)
    - D'Aulaires' Trolls
      - Unbound pages with hand-colored design for cover, circa 1972 (Box 6)
    - Wings for Per
      - Magazines and related research, circa 1944; 13 (Box 7)
      - Magazines and related research, circa 1944; 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Material Housed in Custom Manuscript Boxes
    - Abraham Lincoln
      - Preliminary sketch book with manuscript notes, hand-colored illustration, drawings, sketches, circa 1939 (Box 9)
      - Preliminary sketch book including conceptual designs for the title, color concepts, manuscript pages, circa 1939 (Box 9)
      - Bound sketchbook containing field sketches and notes, circa 1939 (Box 9)
      - Paste-up with hand-colored layouts, circa 1939 (Box 10)
      - Uncut page proofs for 1939 first edition with one page manuscript in Ingri's hand (Box 10)
      - 2 set of page proofs, 1 set with signed black and white proof laid in, for reissue of 1957 (Box 10)
      - Unbound publisher's proof laid into two dust jackets, undated (Box 10)
    - Animals Everywhere
      - Panel panorama with hand-colored illustration comprising the final work, circa 1940 (Box 11)
      - Published proof in three gatherings, plus end papers, used for reissue of 1954 (Box 11)
      - Printed version in panorama form, bound in plain blue cloth with original drawing of boy and tiger on cover, 1954 (Box 11)
    - Benjamin Franklin
      - Manuscript in miniature with drawings, two hand-colored illustrations, circa 1950 (Box 12)
      - Manuscript and typed proverbs, sayings and quotes, circa 1950 (Box 12)
      - Sketch book (14 leaves) and end papers, circa 1950 (Box 12)
      - Sketch book (18 leaves) and end papers, circa 1950 (Box 12)
      - Dummy, titles page, and 2 pages of text with handwritten comments, circa 1950 (Box 12)
      - Publisher's unbound proof with dust jacket, circa 1950 (Box 12)
      - 60 original color illustrations; 5 pencil drawings; 13 hand-colored illustrations; proof of dust jacket, circa 1950 (Box 13)
    - Buffalo Bill
      - 16 original hand-colored illustrations; trial image including title, front cover, dust jacket, circa 1952 (Box 14)
      - Black and white, pencil, and hand-colored illustrations, circa 1952 (Box 15)
      - Unbound proof in 3 signatures, circa 1952 (Box 15)
    - Columbus
      - Preliminary sketches: blank hard cover with loose sketches and notes on end papers consisting of 58 leaves some on acetate including title page design; full page drawings; text; drawings; 2 hand-colored illustrations; "Shipwreck" drawings; 1 charcoal color sketch; title page, circa 1955 (Box 16)
      - Preliminary sketches including blank hard cover with loose sketches, 2 hand-colored illustrations, 5 crayon drawings, 8 pages typescript, 2 manuscript pages, circa 1955 (Box 16)
      - 7 pastel drawing, 1 acetate drawing, circa 1955 (Box 16)
      - Bound preliminary sketchbook of 23 leaves; 11 pages with manuscript text, circa 1955 (Box 16)
      - Complete set of blue line proofs, corrected, circa 1955 (Box 17)
      - Set of galleys, corrected, circa 1955 (Box 17)
      - Unbound proofs, circa 1955 (Box 17)
      - Final dummy in blank covers with end papers and frontispiece; title page in manuscript plus 53 leaves with paste-up text and original drawings, circa 1955 (Box 17)
      - Dummy in 4 gatherings including color and pencil illustrations and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's manuscript notes, circa 1955 (Box 17)
      - Typescript with corrections, circa 1955 (Box 17)
      - 16 matted drawings on acetates, circa 1955 (Box 18)
    - Don't Count Your Chicks
      - Bound early draft with pencil drawing of a round chicken on front cover; drawings and illustrations, circa 1943 (Box 19)
      - Bound early draft with pencil drawing of chick on cover includes original drawings, text, notes, circa 1943 (Box 19)
      - Bound early mock-up with pictorial jacket illustration in reverse; pasted in front end papers in reverse; 18 leaves with mounted text and proof illustrations, circa 1943 (Box 19)
      - Publisher's early proof in 5 gatherings and end papers for paperback edition, circa 1943 (Box 19)
    - Foxie
      - Bound preliminary sketch book with end papers, circa 1949 (Box 20)
      - Bound preliminary sketch book with double end papers, circa 1949 (Box 20)
      - Un-bound publisher's proof in 5 unsewn signatures, and end papers, circa 1949 (Box 20)
    - George Washington
      - Bound preliminary sketchbook, circa 1936 (Box 21)
      - Dummy, 4 signatures; typed letter, signed, from Lillian Glaser to Peggy Lesser with response from Lesser, circa 1936 (Box 21)
      - Color proof for front cover with black and white proof signed by Edgar, circa 1936 (Box 21)
      - 2 original hand-colored designs for dust jacket, circa 1936 (Box 21)
      - 12 matted color proofs, circa 1936 (Box 21)
    - Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths
      - Original typescript in 9 stapled gatherings with numerous manuscript notes and corrections; correspondence; handwritten index on lined paper, circa 1962 (Box 22)
      - Early mock-up of mounted typescript pages with corrections and original drawings and sketches, circa 1962 (Box 22)
      - Mock-up in folder with cover illustrations; pasted-in proof of text and original illustrations, circa 1962 (Box 23)
      - Typescript with corrections: half-title, title, list of books, copy write; dedication and contents in 2 pages; pages of text; pages of index, circa 1962 (Box 24)
      - Working sketches while on site in Greece bound in black notebook, circa 1962 (Box 24)
      - Set of unbound proofs marked "Corrected Version," unbound proof in jacket, circa 1962 (Box 25)
      - Robert Graves correspondence, undated (Box 26)
      - Large group of original drawings and sketches in 19 titled gatherings, color drawing for the cover and a manuscript and typescript index, circa 1962 (Box 27)
    - Leif the Lucky
      - Bound sketchbook and end paper, circa 1941 (Box 28)
      - Preliminary dummy with colored and black and white drawings and sketches including conceptual drawings for the cover, circa 1941 (Box 28)
      - Bound paste-up: final version with pasted in proofs of text and illustrations in blue covers, circa 1941 (Box 28)
      - Dummy titled "Leif the First Story of America," with original hand-colored illustrations, circa 1941 (Box 29)
      - Unbound publisher's proof in 3 gatherings with end papers, 1941 (Box 29)
      - Unbound publisher's proof in 3 gatherings without end papers, 1941 (Box 29)
      - Early artist conceptual draft of 65 leaves, circa 1941 (Box 29)
      - Set of proofs including 20 hand-colored illustrations, circa 1941 (Box 30)
    - The Magic Rug
      - Preliminary sketchbooks: 30 pages with handwritten text and pencil drawings; end papers with drawings, laid in; color drawings, circa 1931 (Box 31)
      - Typescript pages, corrected, circa 1931 (Box 31)
    - Nils
      - Original conceptual drawing, some with overlay, photostats of dust jacket; early version of title; preliminary sketches, circa 1948 (Box 32)
      - Unbound paste-up in proof dust jacket in reverse, circa 1948 (Box 32)
      - Paste-up for color illustrations, in 8-single sewn leaves, with folio size end papers and 2 single pages, circa 1948 (Box 32)
      - Paste-up for color illustrations, in 8 single-sewn leaves, with folio size end papers and 2 single pages, circa 1948 (Box 32)
    - Norse Gods and Giants
      - Typescripts with corrections and printed contents; corrections to "Reader's Companion", circa 1967 (Box 33)
      - Typescript of early draft with written corrections in binder, circa 1967 (Box 33)
      - Copy of typed manuscript, carbon copies, typed table of contents, circa 1967 (Box 33)
      - Typed manuscript in Norwegian with manuscript corrections, sketches, circa 1967 (Box 33)
      - Editorial correspondence in Ingri's hand; manuscript pages with handwritten corrections; handwritten pages from editor; handwritten pages containing suggestions, corrections, and background. Re-typed pages with manuscript pages, circa 1967 (Box 34)
      - Early dummy with preliminary sketches, unbound, manuscript text with some tipped in on slips, circa 1967 (Box 35)
      - Preliminary mock-up with sketches; 10 signatures plus end papers, circa 1967 (Box 35)
      - Black and white sketches and drawings, including title page; color illustrations in mixed media; pen and ink sketches, circa 1967 (Box 35)
      - Preliminary page proofs with typescript introduction; corrections; index; cover checklist from publisher, circa 1967 (Box 36)
      - Galleys marked first proof with notes; contents "Second proof", circa 1967 (Box 36)
      - Publisher's unbound proof in 10 gatherings, circa 1967 (Box 36)
    - Ola
      - Typescript, corrected, circa 1932 (Box 37)
      - Handwritten manuscript, circa 1932 (Box 37)
      - Artist dummy with hand-colored illustrations, drawings and sketches, circa 1932 (Box 37)
      - Hand-colored illustrations with matching proofs, circa 1932 (Box 38)
    - Ola and Blakken and Line, Sine, Trine
      - Dummy with original drawings and handwritten text; inserted proofs and clipped text, circa 1933 (Box 39)
      - Unbound publisher's proof with dust jacket and end papers in photostats, circa 1933 (Box 39)
    - D'Aulaires' Trolls
      - Three layouts with preliminary sketches, guide sheet, drawing with color background, circa 1972 (Box 40)
      - Bound preliminary dummy with some loose pages and preliminary sketches, circa 1972 (Box 41)
      - Mock-up with pasted text and illustrations, circa 1972 (Box 41)
      - Bound final mock-up in dust jacket, 4 original drawings for half-title, circa 1972 (Box 41)
      - Unbound publisher's proof in 6 gatherings, no end papers, circa 1972 (Box 41)
      - Typescripts with manuscript corrections, circa 1972 (Box 42)
    - The Two Cars
      - Bound sketchbook with pictorial cover, circa 1955 (Box 43)
      - Dummy, pasted text and hand-colored illustrations, notes, jacket layout, circa 1955 (Box 43)
      - Original hand-colored design for front cover; proof for end paper, circa 1955 (Box 43)
      - Publisher's proof, circa 1955 (Box 43)
    - Wings for Per
      - Bound sketch book, book with original pencil drawing and text or notes; overlays, circa 1944 (Box 44)